Master.
先生
There's some progress on another matter.
もう一つ見えてきたことがあります
If the Marquis of Wu'an
もし武安侯が
truly is alive,
本当に生きてるなら
what should we do?
どうすればいいですか？
That will be a blessing for Great Yin.
それなら大胤国は 運に恵まれると言えるだろ
There are palace intrigues up ahead
朝廷では内争あり
and Prince Changxin's rebellion looming behind.
それから長信王が反乱を起こした
The Marquis of Wu'an is a pillar of stability.
武安侯こそが我らの支えなのだ
[Pursuit of Jade]
[逐玉]
[Episode 10]
[第10話]
Father,
父さん
Mother.
母さん
Don't cry.
泣かないで
Master, who is buried behind this nameless stele?
先生 この無字碑には どなたが葬られてますか
Today is Father's birthday.
今日は父さんの誕生日だから
Let's be happy.
楽しく過ごしましょ
That way, Father and Mother can be at peace
そすれば空の上の父さんと母さんも
watching us from heaven.
安心できるでしょ
Fan Erniu. Meng Lihua.
樊二牛 孟梨花
Fan...
樊…
Could they have been using another surname?
まさか 別の苗字を使っているのか
The current situation is complicated.
今の状況は複雑で
So much helplessness lies beneath.
裏にはたくさんの苦情があるんだ
When the time is right,
時が来れば
I will tell you everything.
すべてを教えるんだ
It's been 16 years.
もう十六年が経った
It's time for the truth to come to light.
そろそろ真相を世に明かす時だ
Zheng, burn the paper money.
義兄さん お供えをしましょう
There's still some paper money at home.
家にはお焚き上げ用の紙幣が まだ残っているから
When we get back, burn some for your parents too.
帰ったら あなたの両親にも供えてあげて
Does burning these things...
こういうものを供えても
really work?
本当に意味があるのか
Of course.
もちろん
People burn paper money during festivals
みんなは節句のごとに お焚き上げをするのは
to tell their deceased loved ones
亡くなった家族に
that we still remember them.
彼らのことを覚えてるよって 伝えるため
Wenkan,
文檻
promise me one thing.
一つ約束してくれ
If one day I'm gone,
もし わしがこの世を去ったら
you must take good care of
わしの代わりに
the two Fan sisters for me.
樊家の娘たちを必ず守ってくれ
Never let them get involved.
絶対に彼女たちを巻き込むな
Master, you are in such good health.
先生はまだまだお元気なのに
Why say such things?
何を言っていますか
That day will come.
いつかその日が来る
Promise me.
約束してくれ
I promise you.
私は心に刻みます
Don't burn so much.
そんなにたくさんしないで
Don't move.
動かないで
♪ The scenery is as clear as me ♪
♪ 清らかな山と川 私のよう ♪
♪ With very pale colors ♪
♪ 淡く色づけて ♪
♪ Just like the outline in the mirror ♪
♪ 鏡に映る姿のように ♪
♪ I think that's me, being naive ♪
♪ それが何も知らない私なの ♪
♪ Unlocking my heart ♪
♪ そっと心を閉じ込めて ♪
♪ I hid you in my soul ♪
♪ あなたを 私の魂に閉じ込めて ♪
You two look just like Father and Mother.
義兄さんとお姉ちゃん まるで父さんと母さんみたい
Thanks.
ありがとう
You're welcome.
いいえ
Come, Changning.
さあ 長寧
What's wrong with your wrist?
手首はどうした？
The ox cart tipped over when I was collecting pigs yesterday.
昨日 豚を運んでる時に 牛車が転んで
I used my hand to break the fall
手で支えたら
and sprained it.
捻挫した
Changyu's wrist hurts often.
お姉ちゃんは手首がよく痛むの
Butchering pigs is tiring work.
豚を屠るのはとても大変なのよ
Constant strain on the wrist over the years can lead to tendon pain.
手首を酷使すると筋肉を痛めやすい
Luckily the bone isn't affected.
幸いに骨の方は大丈夫
But you need to be careful from now on.
でもこれからは気をつけないと
On the way back later,
私は帰る途中で
I'll get off at the grocery store to buy something.
雑貨屋に寄って買い物をしてくる
You don't have money, right? Here.
金ないでしょ？ 少しあげるわ
No need. I have some.
いや 持ってる
How would you have money?
どうして金を持ってるの？
Get in the cart first.
まず馬車に乗って
Then you two go home first after I'm done shopping.
じゃあ 買い物が済んだら 先に帰ってね
I'll go buy you some tangerine peel candy.
陳皮飴を買ってくるから
Okay.
分かった
Changyu is the best.
お姉ちゃんが大好き
You...
あんた
People keep dying
何度も何度も
in Xigu Lane.
西固巷で人が死んだのは
Maybe we've provoked
何かよくないものに
some kind of spirit.
招かれたのかしら
It's bad luck.
縁起が悪いね
Exactly.
そうよ
It seems this rice water isn't enough.
どうやら この米のとぎ汁じゃ足りないわ
In a moment,
後で
I need to find some dry mugwort leaves
干した艾の葉を探してきて
and hang them on this door.
門に掛けなければならない
Exactly.
そうよ
Look at that jinx.
見てよ あの疫病神
She was actually staring at us.
まだ見てるのよ
You're back?
お帰り
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
You look listless.
元気がないわ
Why are you all wet?
なんでびしょ濡れなの？
The snow was deep. It must have been the snow.
道の雪が深くて濡れてしまったの
Wait.
ちょっと待って
Was someone bullying you
誰かにいじめられたの？
and saying bad things about you?
誰かに悪口でも言われたの？
Who dares to do that?
誰が私の悪口を言えるものか
I'd knock their teeth out.
歯が折れるまで殴ってやるわ
I'm going to change my clothes.
着替えてくるね
[Xigu Lane]
[西固巷]
Fan Changyu!
樊長玉
Come out here! Fan Changyu!
出てきて 樊長玉
Fan Changyu! You...
樊長玉 あなた…
Fan Changyu,
樊長玉
your sister pushed our Hutou
あなたの妹が昼頃
down the stairs at noon.
うちの虎頭を階段から 突き落としたの
Look.
ほら 見て
He lost two front teeth.
前歯が二本も 欠けてしまったじゃない
Tell me, what are you going to do about it?
どうするのよ？
My sister has always been weak.
妹はいつも体が弱い
Your grandson is years older than her.
孫さんは妹より 何歳も年上なのに
How could she possibly push him?
彼を押せるはずがない
Well...
これは…
Granny Kang, let's talk this over calmly.
康婆さん 落ち着いて
You're making a scene in front of the neighbors.
家の前で騒いだら ご近所の笑いものになるわ
The Fan family bullied my grandson.
うちの孫が樊家にいじめられたのに
Why should I be afraid of being laughed at?
笑われることなんて 気にしていられるか
Isn't it normal for kids to have
子供の喧嘩は
a few bumps and scrapes when they're playing around?
よくあることじゃない
-Stop shouting. -Whether you have the right
- ここで騒ぐのはやめて - この理屈を言う資格が あるかどうかは
we need to ask Fan Changning first.
まず樊長寧に聞いてからだわ
Changning, come out.
寧娘 出てきて
Come out. It's okay.
大丈夫だから 出ておいで
Changning, come here.
寧娘 こっちにおいで
Come.
おいで
Changyu wants to ask you something.
お姉ちゃんが 聞きたいことがあってね
Come here.
早くおいで
Come.
おいで
Let me ask you.
お姉ちゃんが聞くけど
Did you push Hutou?
あなたは虎頭を押したの？
Look at that.
ほら 見て
Such a little child already knows how to lie.
こんな小さな子も 嘘をついてるなんて
She nodded just now,
さっきは頷いたのに
and now she's shaking her head.
今すぐ首を振った
Fan Changning, I'm asking you.
樊長寧 聞くよ
Don't lie.
嘘をついてはいけない
Lying will make your mouth rot.
嘘をつけば口が腐ばるよ
You know that?
分かった？
Get away!
どいて
How dare you push me!
よくも私を押したね
Is there no justice left?
こんな理不尽なことがあるものか
The Fan family is so arrogant!
樊家はなんて横柄なのよ
They made my grandson like this,
うちの孫をこんな目に遭わせて
and... and she's acting as if she's completely in the right!
彼女はよくも図に乗っているの
Stop shouting!
まだ騒いでみて！
Alright.
もういい
See if I will shove your head
これ以上騒いだら あなたを
into the swill bucket!
残飯の桶に逆さ吊りにしてやる
I held back earlier
さっき我慢してたのは
because I didn't know
うちが誰かに恨まれ
who my family had offended
西固巷に災いをもたらしたか
to bring trouble to Xigu Lane.
分からなかくて
I feel guilty towards the neighbors,
村人たちには申し訳ないと 思ってるけど
but I haven't wronged you.
あなたに申し訳ないじゃない’わ
People keep dying in your family these days.
この頃 あんたの家では いつも死人が出ている
Everyone in the lane knows that you jinxed them!
誰もがあんたのせいだと 知っているわ
You and Mrs. Song gossip about me every day.
宋婆さんといつも 私の悪口を言ってるね
Do you think I don't know?
私が知らないとでも思ったの？
Fine.
いいわ
I'll grant your wish today.
今日は願いを叶えてあげるわ
What are you doing?
何をする気？
The neighbors are watching.
ご近所さんが見てるのよ
Do you dare commit violence here?
まさか乱暴でもする気？
You've already ruined my reputation.
とっくに評判は汚されちゃったのよ
You don't think I still care
彼らがどう思うか
what they think, do you?
私がまだ気にしてると思ってるの？
If I really do something to you,
もし私が本気を出したら
do you think they'll help you?
みんなが助けてくれると思うの？
Changning.
長寧
When I asked if you pushed Hutou just now,
さっき虎頭を押したか聞いたの時
why did you nod first and then shake your head?
どうしてう頷いてから また首を振ったの？
I did push him.
彼を押したけど
But he was too fat.
彼があまりに太ってて
I couldn't move him.
押せなかったの
He chased me,
彼が私を追いかけてきて
fell down the stairs himself,
自分で階段から落ちて
and broke his front teeth.
前歯を折ったの
Hutou said you pushed him!
虎頭はあんたが押したって
Shut up!
黙って！
I knew Hutou fell on his own.
虎頭は自分で転んだって
Why did you push him?
どうして彼を押したの？
He pulled my hair,
髪を引っ張って
snatched my candy,
飴も奪った
threw rice water on me,
それに米のとぎ汁をかけてきたの
and called me a jinx's sister,
私は疫病神の妹だから
saying I needed a splash of water to get rid of my bad luck.
水をかけて厄払いするんだと言った
You filthy old hag who deserves to be buried with no coffin!
この人でなしの婆
Not only do you have a wicked tongue,
自分の言葉で徳を 積まないなら構わないが
you don't even do good deeds for your grandson.
孫のために 徳を積もうとはしないの？
Aren't you afraid the King of Hell
死んで 閻魔様に会ったら
will rip your tongue out after you die?
舌を抜かれても怖くないの？
How am I wicked?
私が徳を積まないって？
Did I kill her parents?
彼女の両親を私が殺したの？
Did I kill all those people who died in her family?
樊家で死んだ人は私が殺したの？
Everyone in Lin'an knows
林安の者なら 誰も知ってるわ
she's a jinx!
彼女が疫病神だとね
Only you and your husband,
あんたとあんたの旦那さんは
who have no one to bury you when you die,
跡継ぎもいない二人だけが
took in this whole cursed family.
疫病神の一家を引き取ったのよ
Maybe one day,
いつの日か
she'll bring you to your death too.
彼女のせいで死ぬわよ
If you ask me,
私に言わせてみれば
the Fan family
樊家はさっさと
should've gotten out of Xigu Lane long ago.
西固巷から出て行くべきよ
Who knows when their enemies will come looking for them.
いつ仇が来るか 分からないからだよ
-Why are you so mean? -If I'm going to jinx anyone to death,
- そんなに口が悪いの？ - たとえ人を死なせる存在でも
you'll be the first one, you old hag.
真っ先にあなたを死なせるわ
Why should I leave Xigu Lane?
西固巷から出て行くって なんで？
If you're so scared, you leave.
怖いなら自分で 出ていけばいいじゃない
And listen—
それに
if you ever
これから先
lay a finger on Fan Changning again,
樊長寧の髪一本にでも触れたら
whichever hand you use, I'll cut it off.
触れた手を切り落とすわ
You think I'm scared of you?
怖がるわけないでしょ
Don't try to scare me.
脅かさないで
Scare you?
脅かす？
I can chop a pig's trotter clean off with one stroke.
豚足なら一刀で断ち切れるわ
Your hand would be even easier.
あなたの手ならもっと簡単よ
Left or right?
左手と右手
Which one do you want to keep?
どっちを残したいの？
-How about neither? -Don't!
- いっそ両方とも切るか - やめて
Hutou!
虎頭
Hu...
虎…
Grandma!
お婆ちゃん
Karma!
天罰よ！
This is instant karma!
これが天罰なの！
You saw that, right?
みんな 見たでしょ
Changyu and I didn't touch this old woman.
私たちも彼女には触れていないわ
She fell on her own.
この婆が自分で転んだのよ
It was her! She kicked me!
彼女に蹴られたの
Granny Kang,
康婆さん
we were all watching.
みんな ちゃんと見てたわよ
You fell on your own.
自分で転んだの
You must have been too vicious with your words,
口の悪さがたたって
so heaven punished you.
天に見放されたのね
Exactly.
そうよ
It was this jinx! She jinxed me!
この疫病神よ 彼女のせいだ
Get lost! Or I'll jinx you to death!
さっさと出ていけ！ 私のせいで死なせるかもよ
Granny Kang,
康婆さん
be careful.
ゆっくりね
Or you may knock your teeth out.
転んで歯を折っても
Don't blame Changyu for that too.
長玉のせいにしないでよ
Changning.
長寧
in the future, if anyone bullies you outside,
これから外で嫌なことがあったら
come back and tell me, alright?
姉ちゃんに教えていい？
How about you...
あのね
not wait for the New Year?
お正月を待たずに
Just go now.
先に行ったらどう？
Just because of a few words from others,
他人の言葉に惑わされて
you want to chase me away?
私を追い出すつもり？
My family's troubles
うちの不運なことが
have already dragged you in twice.
二度もあなたに及んだ
You don't owe me anything anymore.
もう私に何も負ってないわ
If you cut ties with us sooner,
うちと早く縁を切れば
you'll be safer.
あなたも安全でいられる
You believe that woman's words?
あの女の言葉を信じるのか
No.
信じないわ
I don't believe in fate,
私は運命なんて信じてない
nor in that nonsense about being a cursed star
生涯孤独な運命だとか
who brings misfortune.
相性が悪いとかいう噂も信じてない
I just think that those people
ただあの人たちは
won't let my family go easily,
簡単にうちを 見逃せないと思ってる
so I don't want to drag you down with us.
あなたを巻き込みたくないの
If you think you can push me away
私のためだと思って
just because it's for my own good,
縁を切れるなら
then what about Changning?
じゃあ 寧娘は？
Are you going to cut ties with her too?
彼女とも縁を切れるのか？
I can't.
だめ
She's too young.
彼女はまだ小さいから
I have to keep her with me.
私が連れて行かなきゃ
So,
つまり
you're only driving me away, is that it?
私だけを追い出すつもりなのか
You're not the type to take an insult lying down.
君は黙って 我慢するような人じゃない
If someone splashes water on you,
水をかけられたなら
just teach them a lesson right then and there.
その場でやり返せばいい
There's a saying I once heard from Mr. Wang:
王叔父さんから聞いたことがある
"The law does not punish the masses."
律法は大勢の方に罪を問わないって
It means that if a large group of people breaks the law,
つまり罪を犯した人が多過ぎるなら
the authorities usually won't punish them all.
役所は全員を処罰しないってこと
Now the whole town is gossiping about me
今私の噂を流してるのは
behind my back.
この町に住んでる全員よ
I might be able to deal with one of them,
一人なら躾けられるけど
but can I deal with them all?
町の全員を躾けるわけないでしょ
[Young Xie Zheng]
[少年の謝征]
[Young Wei Xuan]
[少年の魏宣]
Then have you ever heard of the saying
じゃあ 一罰百戒という言葉を
"make an example of someone"?
聞いたことがある？
Human nature is evil.
人間の本性は悪いから
If you're weak and easy to bully,
君が弱いなら苛められる
no matter how kind you are,
例えどんな優しくしても
no one will help you.
君を助ける人はいない
But if you rise to power,
しかしもし君が権力を握っていたら
even if you've done terrible things,
例え天理に悖ることをしても
plenty of people will rush to flatter you.
君にすり寄る人が大勢いる
Superstitions are just meant to confuse people.
鬼神の話なんて 人を惑わすためのものだ
Like the candy that hit Granny Kang just now—
康婆さんを投げつけた飴のように
in her eyes,
彼女にしてみれば
it was just a ghost playing tricks.
鬼神の仕業でしかない
You can say these things to me,
私にそういう話をするのはいい
but if you start distancing yourself
だが もしそれで
from Mr. Zhao and Mrs. Zhao because of it,
趙叔父さんたちと疎遠になったら
they will be heartbroken.
彼らは悲しむぞ
Then take what I said earlier
じゃあ さっきのは
as a moment of impulse.
気が立ってしまった
Please stay.
ここにいて
So it's up to you
行かせたい時は行け
whether I leave or stay, huh?
残らせたい時は 残ってくれと言ったりして
You've got some nerve.
よくもこんな...
Don't be mad.
怒らないでよ
The candy I bought you wasn't meant for that.
あげた飴は そういう使い方するものじゃないわ
You should have gone and found some pebbles.
小石を拾えば？
Candy is expensive.
飴は高いの
♪ The scenery is as clear as me ♪
♪ 清らかな山と川 私のよう ♪
It was not worth it.
割に合わないわ
♪ With very pale colors ♪
♪ 淡く色づけて ♪
♪ Just like the outline in the mirror ♪
♪ 鏡に映る姿のように ♪
♪ I think that's me, being naive ♪
♪ それが何も知らない私なの ♪
♪ Unlocking my heart ♪
♪ そっと心を閉じ込めて ♪
I never had the chance to ask before.
この前 聞く機会がなかったけど
♪ I hid you in my soul ♪
♪ あなたを 私の魂に閉じ込めて ♪
Why did you become an armed escort and risk your life?
なぜ命懸けで用心棒をやってるの？
Because...
それは
♪ The moon is as quiet as me ♪
♪ この月の光は穏やかに 私のよう ♪
there are things I simply must do.
やらねばならぬことがあるからだ
Just like how
君が父の肉屋を
♪ The light shines ♪
♪ 光が差し込んで ♪
you want to keep running your father's butcher shop.
継ぎたいのと同じだ
♪ It illuminates the turbulence in my heart ♪
♪ 胸に隠した傷を照らす ♪
My father
私の父にも
♪ It seems to be the fire of love ♪
♪ まるで愛の炎のよう♪
also had unfinished business.
やり残したことがある
♪ Just a few sparks ♪
♪ ほんの少しだけでも ♪
I want to finish it for him.
代わりにやり遂げたいんだ
♪ Let me hide in your heart ♪
♪ あなたの心に隠れさせて ♪
So your family ran an escort agency?
だから 実家は運送屋で
And you were the Young Master?
あなたが運送屋の若旦那だったの？
♪ I pray that our love ♪
♪ 私たちの愛を願うよ ♪
♪ Will never end ♪
♪ ずっと離れないで ♪
Rebuilding an escort agency costs a lot of money.
運送屋の再建には 大金がかかるでしょ
♪ It's worth my foolishly waiting ♪
♪ 私は一生をかけても ♪
♪ For a lifetime ♪
♪ 待つことを悔やまない ♪
When I have some money to spare,
もし余裕ができたら
I can help you out.
私が援助してあげるわ
♪ Clear and quiet as me ♪
♪ 清らかな私 穏やかな私 ♪
No need.
結構だ
I haven't repaid you
君から受けた命の恩は
for saving my life yet.
まだ報いていない
♪ So what if we encounter difficulties? ♪
♪ 棘があっても構わない ♪
That's a completely different matter.
それは別の話よ
♪ I pray that our love will not be like sand ♪
♪ 私は愛を願うよ ♪
When you agreed to marry into my family,
前に入り婿を受け入れてくれた時
♪ Slipping into the sea ♪
♪ 砂が海に 沈むようにはならないで ♪
we were already even.
もう貸し借りないわ
♪ I'd rather use this life ♪
♪ 私はこの一生をかけても ♪
♪ To guard our love forever ♪
♪ 長く愛を守りたいの ♪
You want to be even with me?
私と貸し借りをなくしたいのか
♪ Clear and quiet as me ♪
♪ 清らかな私 穏やかな私 ♪
That's not what I meant.
そういう意味じゃないの
♪ Why do we need to seek cause and effect ♪
♪ どうして因果を求めるの ♪
We've known each other for so long,
長く知り合ってるのに
yet I still don't know when your birthday is.
君の誕生日がまだ分からない
My birthday is easy to remember.
私の誕生日は覚えやすいわ
It's 2 days after the Lantern Festival.
上元の節の二日後で
The holiday spirit is still strong then.
まだ正月の雰囲気が残ってて
It's very lively.
にぎやかなのよ
What do you want?
何が欲しい？
I want my family all together,
家族がみんな一緒に
safe and sound.
平穏無事に暮らすこと
And if in the spring,
春になったら
I could keep another litter of piglets, that would be even better.
子豚を飼えたらもっといいわ
[Capital]
[京城]
Your Majesty, I have a proposal.
臣下に上奏いたします
Grand Tutor, please go ahead.
太傅 どうぞ言って
Your Majesty,
陛下
the weather has been erratic this year.
今年は天候不順で
The land is barren, and the crops have failed.
土地が干からび 作物が実りません
In this year of disaster,
今はまさに凶作の年です
if we still transport grain to the front line,
このまま備蓄食糧を 戦線に送り続ければ
I fear it will cause a refugee crisis
多くの流民が出る恐れがあり
and shake the foundation of the state.
国の基礎を揺るがすことになります
Your Majesty, I implore you
陛下 どうか前線への
to revoke the restoration order for the front line.
補給命令をお取り下げください
I humbly ask for Your Majesty's judgment.
陛下の御聖断を
The situation on the front line changes rapidly.
前線の戦況はすぐに変わりものです
Even the Marquis of Wu'an has fallen in battle.
武安侯でさえも戦場で 命を落としました
Provisions before a great battle are of the utmost importance.
大戦を前に兵糧は何より大切です
How can we easily revoke the order?
軽々しく取り下げられましょうか
After years of war,
今は長年戦乱が続き
the treasury is now empty and cannot bear the burden.
国庫は底を尽き もはや支えることはできません
If the treasury is empty, levy grain locally
国庫が尽きたのなら 現地で食糧を徴収して
to solve the urgent need.
当面の急場をしのげば良いです
After we pacify Chongzhou,
崇州を平定した後で
we can return it to the people.
民に返せば良いのです
It is deep winter now, and the end of the year is approaching.
今は真冬にあたり 年越しも間近です
The people's surplus grain is not enough to fill their own stomachs.
民は蓄えだけでは足らないのに
Levying grain locally?
現地で食糧を徴収すれば
Prime Minister Wei,
魏丞相
are you not worried
民衆の反乱を
that it will incite a civil uprising?
招くことが心配ではありませんか
The front line is engulfed in flames of war,
前線では戦火が絶えず
and our soldiers are fighting bloody battles.
兵士たちは命を懸けて戦っています
Provisions are the lifeline of the army.
兵糧は軍の生命線であり
How can they go a day without them?
一日たりとも 欠かすことはできません
If the enemy takes this chance to march south and breach our cities,
もし敵がこの機に乗じて 南下し城を破れば
I fear it will bring disaster and ruin to our nation.
国が滅びる災いを 招くかもしれません
Grand Tutor,
太傅
do you dare to bear such a heavy responsibility alone?
その責任を 一身に負えるのでしょうか
Surely, Grand Tutor Li,
李太傅も
you do not wish to repeat the tragedy of 16 years ago,
十六年前に瑾州城に兵糧が届かず
when provisions failed to reach Jinzhou City,
敵に町を焼き討ちにされた悲劇を
leading to its massacre?
もう二度と 繰り返したくないはずです
Prime Minister Wei is farsighted.
魏丞相は考えが深く
He is truly the most loyal subject of Great Yin.
実に我が大胤国一の忠臣なり
[Diligent and Virtuous]
[勤政親賢]
Prime Minister Wei is loyal and righteous.
魏丞相は国のために尽くす忠臣です
[Wei Residence]
[魏府]
Uncle,
叔父さん
when I grow up, I want to be like my father,
大きくなったら父上のように
fighting on the battlefield.
戦場に立つんだ
[Mrs. Wei]
[魏夫人]
Prime Minister.
宰相様
Come in.
入れ
Prime Minister, please have some ginseng tea.
宰相様 参茶をどうぞ
Have Zheng's remains
征児の遺体は
still not been found?
まだ見つからないのでしょうか
This child is of the Wei family's bloodline.
あの子は魏家の血を引いており
And he was raised with such care by you.
幼い頃から 宰相様に手厚く育てられてきました
They say a maternal uncle is like a second father.
母方の兄が一番の身内と言いますが
It's such a pity that he died like this.
こうして亡くなるとは 実に惜しいです
Please take care of yourself, Prime Minister.
宰相様 どうかお体を大切に
-And Xuan... -Please go back.
- 宣児の方も… - 夫人 引き返しなさい
I spoke out of turn.
私が余計なことを言いました
I beg your forgiveness, Prime Minister.
どうかお許しください
I shall take my leave.
では これで失礼いたします
Prime Minister,
宰相様
He Jingyuan, Governor of Jizhou,
霽州長官賀敬元が
has sent a brocade box by fast horse.
速馬で錦箱一つ届けられました
[To Prime Minister Wei of Great Yin]
[大胤国魏丞相親展]
He has always been cautious.
彼はいつも慎重だ
[To Wei Qilin]
[魏祁林より]
To General Suituo,
随拓将軍へ
Jinzhou is in critical danger.
瑾州の戦況は切迫しております
I must return to the capital for an urgent matter.
急用のため 都へ戻ることになりました
Therefore, I am sending my household general, Wei Qilin,
そこで部下の魏祁林に兵符を持たせ
to request immediate reinforcements with the Tiger Tally
すぐに援軍を発してください
to resist Beijue together
共に北厥国を防ぎ
and save Crown Prince Chengde.
承德太子を救いましょう
General, Wei Yan.
中郎将 魏厳
Eighth day of the fifth month, the 26th year of Taikang.
泰康二十六年五月八日
It seems He Jingyuan
どうやら賀敬元は
is using his own life as leverage
自分の命をかけて
to make me spare the two daughters of that traitor.
あの二人の裏切り者の娘を 許すよう迫っているようだなな
He Jingyuan is so bold.
この大胆な賀敬元め
Prime Minister, you shouldn't have been soft-hearted back then
宰相様 あの時 情けをかけ
and stopped searching for Wei Qilin's body.
魏祁林の遺体捜しを 諦めるべきではなかったのです
Zheng's
征児が
sudden investigation into the Jinzhou massacre
急に瑾州の惨事を調べ始めたのは
must have been instigated by someone with ulterior motives.
何者かが裏で 糸を引いているに違いない
Now,
今や
even He Jingyuan goes against my orders.
賀敬元まで 言うことを聞かなくなった
Why don't you let me
いっそ 私に
go and get rid of He Jingyuan?
賀敬元を始末させてください
The battle in Chongzhou is critical right now.
今は崇州の戦いが長引いている
If I lose a weapon like He Jingyuan,
ここで賀敬元という刃まで失ったら
the Northwest will be in peril.
西北の地は危険になるのではないか
I see.
はい
Forget it.
もういい
They are just two girls.
たかが娘二人ではないか
[To Wei Qilin]
[魏祁林 拝啓]
Let them live.
生かしておけ
How much trouble can they possibly cause?
大したことはできない
Lord Li?
李大人
[Fill Your Belly]
[いっぱい食べる]
Your husband is not home today?
旦那さんは今日は留守？
He went out on business.
用事で出かけております
Do you need him for something, My Lord?
何かご用でしょうか
Just asking casually.
ちょっと聞いただけ
By the way,
そうだ
regarding the case involving your family,
お宅の事件について
I have figured out everything.
全て明らかにした
Who did it?
誰がやったのですか
The Qingzhou Government Office found that the attacks on your family
霽州府の調べでは お宅が何度も襲われたのは
stemmed from an escort mission your father undertook years ago.
お父さんがかつて ある荷物を護送したからだ
Rumor has it that it involved a treasure map
噂によると それは前王朝の皇室が
left by the previous dynasty's royal family.
残した宝の地図だそうだ
Over a decade ago,
十数年前
everyone in the escort agency was killed.
運送屋の者は皆殺しにされた
Only your father survived.
お父上だけが九死に一生を得て
That was why he could settle down here in Lin'an Town all these years.
この林安鎮で 穏やかに暮らすことができた
After the turmoil in Chongzhou,
崇州戦乱の後
the treasure map was brought up again.
宝の地図の噂が また蒸し返されました
The bandits from Qingfeng Stronghold tracked down your father,
清風寨の山賊が お父さんの行方を突き止め
which is why they repeatedly attacked your home—
だから何度も家に押し入った
to get that treasure map.
狙いはこの宝の地図だ
Treasure map?
宝の地図？
I've never heard my parents mention it.
両親から聞いたことはありません
Yes.
うん
So, rumors can be deadly.
だから 噂は人を苦しめるものだ
Why did Li Huaian make up such a lie
なぜ李懐安は嘘をついて
just to close the case?
事件を終結させようとするの？
My parents...
私の両親は
died just because of a rumor?
ただの噂で命を落としたのですか
A few days ago, the rebels in Chongzhou announced
数日前 崇州の反乱軍が 知らせを出し
that they had already found the treasure map.
宝の地図は手に入れたそうだ
The Qingfeng Stronghold bandits won't come to town anymore.
清風寨の山賊が この町にこないだろう
You can rest assured.
安心して
[Memorial Tablet of Meng Lihua] [Memorial Tablet of Fan Erniu]
[孟梨花の神位] [樊氏二牛の神位]
If there's a chance to catch those bandits
もし悪党どもを捕らえる機会があり
and let my parents rest in peace,
両親の無念を晴らせるなら
I am at your command, My Lord.
何なりと李大人のご指示に従います
[Fill Your Belly]
[いっぱい食べる]
This is the relief fund sent
これは霽州長官の賀大人が 民を思いやり
concern for the people. He specially appointed me to deliver it.
私に届けさせた救済金
Is it all for me?
全部私にくれますか？
For those who suffered at the hands of the Qingfeng Stronghold bandits
今回 清風寨の山賊の毒牙にかかり
and lost family members,
家族を亡くした方には
the government has issued consolation money.
役所から救済金が支給されている
It's not just your family.
お宅だけではない
The standard is 10 taels per person.
慣例により 一人十両となってるが
Here is 30 taels of silver.
こちらは三十両で
Please accept it.
どうぞ受け取って
Dry weather!
空気が乾いています
Beware of fire!
火の用心
It's flying over!
飛んできた
Changyu,
お姉ちゃん
you talked in your sleep again last night.
昨日の夜 また寝言を言ってたよ
What did I say?
何を言ったの？
You said you were afraid the spices from out of town weren't authentic.
よその香辛料は偽物かもって
You said,
あと五種類の香辛料じゃ足りない
"Five spices aren't enough, we need six."
六種類の香辛料にしないとって
Then you said that if Zheng left,
それに 義兄さんが離れてしまったら
you'd never find such a handsome husband again.
あんなに立派な夫は 二度と見つからないって
Keep your voice down.
ちょっと 声を控えて
Changyu,
お姉ちゃん
we don't have to move anymore?
もう引っ越さなくていいの？
But I already told the others in the village
でも 村のみんなには
that we were moving.
引っ越すって言っちゃった
It's so embarrassing not to move now.
今さらやめたら 恥ずかしいよ
Can we move out for a little while,
ちょっとだけ引っ越して
then move back?
また戻っていいの？
That would count as moving.
引っ越したことになるでしょ
Why are you so smart?
なんてそんなに賢いの
How about this?
じゃあ こうして
Tell them
みんなに
we don't have to move anymore,
もう引っ越さないって伝えて
and give them some candy.
それからお菓子をあげれば
Then they won't laugh at you.
もう笑ったりしないわ
Changyu,
お姉ちゃん
when will you go back to sleep with Zheng?
いつまで義兄さんと一緒に寝るの？
You're squeezing into my small bed every day.
毎日この小さい寝床に 一緒に寝るから
It's hard for me to even turn over.
寝返りも打てないの
Mrs. Zhao says
叔母さんが言ったよ
that a husband and wife should sleep together for life.
夫婦はずっと一緒に寝るものなのよ
What?
何よ
Are you sick of me already?
もう私のこと嫌がってる？
I don't care.
知らないわよ
I want to sleep with you.
あなたとずっと一緒に寝るんだから
For a lifetime!
一生だよ
How dare you be sick of me!
私のこと嫌がってね
Take that!
嫌がってるなんて
Are you still sick of me?
まだ嫌がるの？
-No! -Are you?
- 嫌わない - まだ嫌がるの？
You're not, are you?
もう嫌がらなくなったでしょ
I yield.
降参だよ
Beg for mercy, quickly!
早く降参して
Changyu!
お姉ちゃん
All you do is eat.
食いしん坊め
You're getting so fat.
そんなに太って
I wonder if you can still fly.
まだ飛べるのか
Go now.
行け
[Xigu Lane]
[西固巷]
Let's go.
さあ 行こう
Let's go!
行こう
Morning, Mrs. Fan.
樊姉さん おはよう
Morning.
おはよう
Lord Li?
李大人
Why are you at the Song's house?
なぜ宋家にいるのですか
[Xigu Lane]
[西固巷]
I rented a vacant house from a broker.
仲介人から空き家を借りたのだが
When I got here, I realized it was opposite your home.
来てみたら お宅の向かいだったとは
So this family is named Song?
この家は宋という苗字なのか
Aren't you going back to Jizhou?
霽州へは戻らないのですか
I promised I would find
君の両親を殺した犯人を
the murderer of your parents.
見つけると約束した
I must keep my word.
絶対に約束を守るぞ
Lord Li?
李大人？
To catch the murderer, Lord Li
李大人が犯人を捕まえるため
decided to stay for a while.
しばらく滞在することになった
And he even rented Song Yan's house.
しかも宋硯の家を借りたの
Isn't that a coincidence?
すごい偶然でしょ
What a coincidence indeed.
本当に偶然だな
I won't disturb you two.
では　失礼
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
The falcon is gone.
隼隼が逃げたわ
Maybe the lid wasn't closed tightly last night.
昨夜 蓋を閉め忘れたのかも
After its wings healed, it flew away on its own.
翼が治ったら 自分で飛んでいったの
This falcon has parents of its own.
隼だって 父と母がいる
It needs to go home to find them.
自分の家に帰りたかったのよ
Don't cry.
泣かないで
There's nothing we can do.
仕方ないわ
The falcon has a family too.
隼隼にだって家族がいるんだもの
Don't cry.
もう泣かないの
It will fly back.
また戻って来るぞ
Can you pinky-promise me for the falcon?
義兄さん 隼隼の代わりに 指切りしてくれる？
You're going to leave sooner or later,
いつかここを去るよね
aren't you?
そうでしょう？
In my current situation,
今の私は
loving someone
私が好きになった人は
only puts them in danger.
不幸になるんだ
People
人は
are not deities who cut off emotions and desires.
感情を持たない仙人なんかじゃない
It's hard to control
好きになったら
your feelings.
自分では抑えられないものだ
Don't coax her.
彼女を甘やかさないで
Changning is just a bit lonely.
寧娘はただ寂しいだけなの
I'll buy a cage of chicks in the spring.
春になったらひよこを買ってあげる
With new playmates, she'll forget the falcon.
新しい遊び相手ができたら 隼のことなんて忘れるもの
In the spring,
春になったら
I'll buy you a big cage of chicks, okay?
お姉ちゃんがひよこを たくさん買ってあげるよ
No. I want the falcon.
嫌だ 隼隼でないとだめよ
You don't want that?
いらないの？
I wasn't coaxing her.
甘やかしてなんかいない
To fully tame a falcon,
隼の調教では
you have to let it fly first.
最後に一度放すんだ
Only one that returns
戻って来る隼こそ
is truly tamed.
完全に懐いた隼なんだ
But there's no guarantee it will come back.
だって戻ってこないかもしれない
[Aspiring to the Clouds]
[心向雲端]
So you're really not leaving Lin'an?
本当に林安を離れないの？
I was so happy when I heard the news
この話を聞いて
that I couldn't sleep all night.
うれしくて一晩中眠れなかったわ
I'll show you something.
いい物を見せてあげる
I've been preparing it for a long time.
ずっと前から準備してたの
-Come on. -What is it?
- さあ - 何の物ですか
What are you doing?
どうしたんですか
Look.
見て
The auspicious time has arrived!
令辰です
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[樊記煮込み屋]
[Braised Pork Belly] [Braised Pig's Ear]
[ばら肉の煮込み] [豚耳の煮込み]
Bravo!
よし
Pray to the God of Wealth,
財神様を拝んで
and may your business prosper!
開店したら大儲けよ
What's wrong?
どうしたんですか
Nothing.
ううん
Let's offer the incense.
線香をあげましょう
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[樊記煮込み屋]
Okay.
よかった
What would you like to eat?
何にしますか
Your meat smells delicious.
ここの肉はいい匂いわ
I want a piece that's not too fatty.
脂っこくないのをちょうだい
None of them is too fatty. They're all good.
どれも美味しいですよ
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[樊記煮込み屋]
Pick a big one.
大きいのをちょうだい
Okay.
はい
I'll weigh it for you.
計りますね
Come back often.
今後もよろしくお願いします
Okay.
はい
Changyu?
樊家の嬢さん？
It's me, it's me.
はい 私です
Your shop has been closed for a while.
しばらく店を開けてなかったから
We couldn't buy braised meat anywhere.
煮込み肉が買えなくて困ってたのよ
Turns out you came to Yixiang Restaurant to make it.
溢香楼で作ってたのね
Mrs. Fan
樊姉さんは
is partnering with Yixiang Restaurant now.
今や溢香楼と提携して
She'll sell exclusively here from now on.
ここで専門販売しているの
Ma'am, feel free to come by anytime if you like it.
好きならいつでも来てね
Changyu's pork used to come
前は長玉の豚肉を買うと
with free offal.
いつも臓物をくれたわ
Then I won't be polite.
じゃあ 遠慮なく
Look at this.
これを見てください
I... this...
あの これは…
This time...
今回は…
Well, this time...
いえ 今回は…
Changyu's braised meat
長玉が前に作っていた煮込み肉は
used to be home-style.
家庭の味だったけど
Now that she's with Yixiang Restaurant,
今は溢香楼と提携して
the ingredients and recipe are upgraded.
材料も味付けも秘伝も全部改良した
Let alone offal,
臓物どころか
even the stock is pricier.
苦汁でさえ以前より貴重なのよ
Well,
こんなの
then how can we common folk afford that?
私たち庶民には食べられないわ
Forget it.
いいや
I'll look elsewhere.
もう他の店へ行くわ
We are opening today,
今日は開店初日だから
so we want to start on a lucky note.
縁起を担いで
If you
もし叔母さんが今後
can bring us 5 customers in the future,
五人のお客さんを 連れて来てくれたら
you'll get a 20 percent discount.
二割引き
25 percent off for 10 customers.
十人なら二点五割引
And 30 percent off for 20. How about that?
二十人なら三割引きにします どうですか？
Alright.
分かった
Changyu,
じゃあ 長玉
pick two good pieces of meat for me.
いい肉を二つ選んで
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[樊記煮込み屋]
It's my husband's birthday today.
今日はうちの旦那の誕生日なのよ
Okay.
はい
I guarantee it'll be delicious and generous.
味もよく 分量もたっぷりにしますね
That piece.
じゃあ あれを
I didn't want to offer free offal before,
前はおまけをしたくなかったのに
and the customers were unwilling to accept it.
お客さんは皆嫌がりました
You just said a few words,
あなたは少し話せば
and they rushed to give us money.
皆すんなり買ってくださいました
Qianqian, you're really amazing at doing business.
浅姉さん 本当に商売がお上手ですね
Undercutting isn't business.
値切るだけでは商売じゃない
Mutual benefit is what business is all about.
互いに得をしてこそ 本当の商売なのよ
The great man is he who is in harmony,
立派な人格を持つ人は
in his attributes, with heaven and earth;
徳は天地のように広く
in his brightness, with the sun and moon;
知恵は日月のように明らかで
in his orderly procedure, with the four seasons;
行いは四季のように秩序だっており
and in his relation to what is fortunate and what is calamitous,
吉凶は鬼神のように見通せる
He naturally—
天が動く前に…
Your Lordship honors me with your presence.
侯爺がお越しくださるとは
My wait was not in vain.
待ったかいがありました
Tell me. What is your purpose in coming to the Fan family?
言ってみろ 樊家に来た目的は何だ？
I came to the Fan family
樊家に来たのは
only to see you, Your Lordship.
ただ侯爺にお目にかかるためです
We have known each other since childhood
我々は幼い頃からの知り合いで
and both learned martial arts from General He.
武芸は共に賀将軍から学びました
Since the conflict between the Li and Wei,
李太傅と魏丞相が争い始めてから
we've been avoiding each other.
互いに顔を合わせなくなりました
It has been
あっという間に
over a decade, hasn't it?
十数年になりますな
I am curious now.
今は興味がある
Are you a Li
お前は李派か
or a Wei?
それとも魏派か
I only serve Great Yin
私はただ大胤国のため
and the people.
民のために尽くします
What about you, Your Lordship?
では侯爺は？
Which side are you on now?
どちらの味方ですか
Anyone can say
綺麗事は
pretty words.
誰でも言える
I have always
私は常に
only served myself.
自分のためだけだ
The conflict between Li and Wei has become chaotic.
李太傅と魏丞相の争いは すでに乱局となっています
And you intend to establish your own faction in the future.
これから侯爺は ご独立をなさるつもりですか
Do you wish to make this chaos even worse?
この乱局を さらにかき乱すおつもりですか